A Finding Aid to the National Society of Mural Painters Records, 1895 - circa 2007, in the Archives of American Art aaa.natimurp
Archives of American Art
National Society of Mural Painters records
1895 - circa 2007
aaa.natimurp
Archives of American Art
13.1 Linear feet
The records of the National Society of Mural Painters measure 13.1 linear feet and date from 1895 to circa 2007. The activities of the society are documented through administrative files, membership files, correspondence, committee files, exhibition and competition files, artist files, financial and legal records, printed material, a scrapbook, and photographic materials.
National Society of Mural Painters (New York, N.Y.)
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment. Use of archival audiovisual recordings with no duplicate access copy requires advance notice.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The records of the National Society of Mural Painters were donated to the Archives of American Art by the society in 1965-1966. An later group of records was donated by the National Society of Mural Painters via president Jeff Greene in 2009.
Separated Materials note
In 1963, the National Society of Mural Painters lent 83 photographs of mural paintings and studies for murals, and 25 exhibition boards showing sculptures, mosaics, or mural paintings which listed the artist, medium, title, and location. These records were microfilmed onto reel NSM1 and it is available at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan.
Scope and Contents note
The records of the National Society of Mural Painters measure 13.1 linear feet and date from 1895 to circa 2007. The activities of the society are documented through administrative files, membership files, correspondence, committee files, exhibition and competition files, artist files, financial and legal records, printed material, a scrapbook, and photographic materials.
Administrative files include meeting minutes and agendas, historical information, and newsletter drafts, and the organization's constitution and by-laws. Membership files contain correspondence with members about their applications and acceptance or denial of membership, member voting ballots, and lists of members. General correspondence is with artists, members, organizations, universities, and federal commissions, and documents a wide varity of NSMP activities; additional correspondence is scattered throughout other series. Correspondence is with Charles Baskerville, Arthur Covey, Allyn Cox, Dean Fausett, Ruth Fortel, Edward Lanning, Everett Molinari, Jack Stewart, and Helen Tredwell, as well as with the American Federation of Arts, the Commission of Fine Arts on War Memorials, Fine Arts Federation, and the U. S. Capitol Historical Society.
Committee files document the work of various NSMP standing and ad hoc committees. Exhibition and competition files include correspondence, photographs, catalogs, itineraries, and printed materials for the NSMP's 1976 U.S. Bicentennial celebration projects, including the "Freedom Murals," "Caravan of Freedom," and "Momentous Events in American History." Additional files document the Red Cross Canteen Project, Federal Art Project, the Municipal Art Society exhibition in 1940, New York City subway murals, and other competitions and public art mural projects.
Artist files primarily date from the 1960s through the 1990s and often include biographies, resumes, correspondence, and photographs of works of art. Financial and legal records include the NSMP treasurer's files, ledgers, and miscellany. Also found in the records are printed materials; a mixed media scrapbook dating from 1923-1935; photographs of meetings, events, exhibitions, and works of art; photo collages of members with examples of their works of art. There are also lantern slides of Francis D. Millet in his studio and with his murals, and of J. Scott Williams with his art work.
Biographical/Historical note
Originally named The Mural Painters, the National Society of Mural Painters (NSMP) was founded in 1895 in New York City by a group of artists, including John W. Alexander, Kenyon Cox, Edwin Blashfield, and John LaFarge, who were concerned with the design and execution of mural art for architecture in the United States. The organization's first president was Frederic Crowninshield. For well over one hundred years members of NSMP have created significant and monumental works of art across the country. Many significant American artists have been members and served as past presidents, such as George Biddle, Hildreth Meiére, Arthur S. Covey, Allyn Cox, Helen Treadwell, and Xavier Gonzales, among many others.
Since its founding, the NSMP has collaborated with the Fine Arts Section of the Treasury Department, the federal WPA Arts Project, and the design boards of several World's Fairs. As a member of Artists for Victory, NSMP coordinated the execution of murals for barracks and camps, as well as many triptych alterpieces.
NSMP organizes exhibitions and conductes competitions. In celebration of its one hundredth anniversary, a centennial exhibition was held in October 1995 at the Art Students League. Society members work with other organizations, actively sponsoring legislation for the development and commission of public works of art. Still active today, the current president is Jeff Greene.
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 10 series reflecting the original order of the records.
Series 1: Administrative Files, 1895-circa 2007 (2.2 linear feet; Boxes 1-3)
Series 2: Membership Files, 1915-2001 (1.1 linear feet; Boxes 3-4)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1912-2001 (1.0 linear feet; Boxes 4-5)
Series 4: Committee Files, 1909-1960s (0.3 linear feet; Box 5)
Series 5: Exhibition and Competition Files, 1917-1998 (2.0 linear feet; Boxes 5-7)
Series 6: Artist Files, 1915-1990s (1.3 linear feet; Boxes 7-8, 18)
Series 7: Financial and Legal Records, 1895-1996 (1.5 linear feet; Boxes 8-10)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1915-2000 (0.9 linear feet; Boxes 10-11)
Series 9: Scrapbook, 1923-1935 (0.2 linear feet; Box 11)
Series 10: Photographic Material, circa 1900-1997 (2.5 linear feet; Boxes 12-18)
American Federation of Arts.; Baskerville, Charles, 1896-; Covey, Arthur Sinclair, 1877-1960; Cox, Allyn; Fausett, Dean, 1913-; Federal Art Project; Fine Arts Federation of New York; Fortel, Ruth; Lanning, Edward P.; Millet, Francis Davis, 1846-1912; Molinari, Everett; Municipal Art Society of New York.; Red Cross.; Stewart, Jack; Treadwell, Helen, 1902-; United States Capitol Historical Society.; Williams, J. Scott, (John Scott), b. 1877; American Revolution Bicentennial, 1776-1976; Art--Study and teaching; Artists' studios--Photographs; Lantern slides; Mural painting and decoration--19th century--United States; Mural painting and decoration--20th century--United States; Muralists--United States; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Subways--New York (N.Y.)
- Administrative Files, 1895-circa 2007; Series 1; 2.2 Linear feet Boxes 1-3
  Scope and Contents note
  Administrative files contain material regarding the society's activities, founding, and history and include meeting minutes and agendas, drafts of newsletters, constitution and by-laws, and other miscellaneous documents and one videocassette. Files labeled miscellaneous likely contain duplicates of other material documented throughout the collection.
  - Annual Dinner and Meeting, 1910-1943 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Chapters, Regional, 1940-1941 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Constitution and By-Laws, 1915-1998 (Box 1, Folder 4-7)
  - Guest Register, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Historical Information, circa 1950-circa 2000 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Historical Information, NSMP #1, 1996-1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Letterhead Design, 1940, 2000 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mailing Lists, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1895-1940 (Box 1, Folder 13-23)
  - Meeting Minutes and Agendas, 1940-circa 2007 (Box 2, Folder 1-19)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative Files, Likely Duplicates, 1919-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 20-23)
  - Miscellaneous Administrative Files, Likely Duplicates, 1919-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Newsletters, Drafts, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Website Design and Permissions, circa 1996 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Membership Files, 1915-2001; Series 2; 1.1 Linear feet Boxes 3-4
  Found is correspondence relating to the application, acceptance, and decline of membership from 1916 to 1954 and the 1990s. Also found are lists of contact information for members and voting history and ballots. Correspondence about membership applications and acceptance decisions are found for many artists, including George Biddle, Edward Bruce, Kenyon Cox, Allyn Cox, Philip Evergood, William Gropper, Stefan Hirsch, Tom LaFarge, Geoffrey Norman, Violet Oakley, and Ernest Peixotto, among many others.
  - Applications, 1980s (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Contact Information and Lists, 1915-2001 (Box 3, Folder 5-18)
  - Contact Information and Lists, Honorary, Lifetime, and Professional Members, 1935-2000 (Box 3, Folder 19-21)
  - Correspondence, 1916-1954 (Box 3, Folder 22-32)
  - Correspondence, 1990s (Box 4, Folder 1-2)
  - Deceased Members, 1919-circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 3-5)
  - Membership Cards, 1990s-2000 (Box 4, Folder 6-7)
  - Personnel Index, 1917 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Voting Ballots, 1941, 1996 (Box 4, Folder 9-10)
- Correspondence, 1912-2001; Series 3; 1 Linear feet Boxes 4-5
  Correspondence documents a wide variety of general activities of the NSMP and is with artists, members, organizations, universities, and federal commissions' additional correspondence is scattered throughout other series. Correspondence is with Charles Baskerville, Arthur Covey, Allyn Cox, Dean Fausett, Ruth Fortel, Edward Lanning, Everett Molinari, Jack Stewart, and Helen Tredwell, as well as with the American Federation of Arts, the Commijssion of Fine Arts on War Memorials, Fine Arts Federation, and the U. S. Capitol Historical Society.
  Arrangement note
  Correspondence is arranged in rough alphabetical order. Folders with individual names were transcribed from the original folders may include letters to and from that correspondent.
  - A, 1918-circa 2000 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - American Federation of Art, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Andors, Rhoda, 1989-1993 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Artists League of America, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - B, circa 1912-circa 1952 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Baehr, Francine, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Baskerville, Charles, 1957-1960 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - C, circa 1912-1976 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Case, Elizabeth, 1995 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Columbia University, 1918-1921 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Commission of Fine Arts on War Memorials, 1946 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Covey, Arthur, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Cox, Allyn, 1960-1963 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - D, circa 1912-circa 1952 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - E, circa 1912-1977 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - F, circa 1912-1978 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Fausett, Dean, 1960s-1980s (Box 4, Folder 27-29)
  - Fine Arts Federation, 1917-1941 (Box 4, Folder 30-31)
  - Fortel, Ruth, 2000 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Franklin Mint, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - G, circa 1912-1999 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Gonzalez, Xavier, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - H, circa 1912-1986 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Harding, Robert Jr., 2000s (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Irwin, Howard Lee, 1940-1941 (Box 4, Folder 38-39)
  - J, 1977-1986 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Juta, Jan, 1975-1976 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - K, circa 1912-circa 1952 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - L, circa 1912-1969 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Lanning, Edward, 1970s (Box 4, Folder 44)
  - M, circa 1912-1977 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Mahoney, James Owen, 1938 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Molinari, Everett, 1980-1999 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Mortellito, Domenico, 1938-1939 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - N, circa 1912-1977 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - NanTandy, 1980s (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Norman, Geoffrey, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Orme, Lydia Gardner, 1941-1942 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - P, circa 1912-1979 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - Ross, Louis, 1938-1940 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - S, circa 1912-1976 (Box 4, Folder 55)
  - Selection of Fine Arts, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  - Slobodkin, Louis, 1939-1940 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  - Stewart, Jack, 1997-2001 (Box 4, Folder 58-60)
  - T, circa 1912-1981 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Tobey, Alton, 1977-1993 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Treadwell, Helen, 1960s-1980s (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - U, circa 1912-1999 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - U.S. Capitol Historical Society, 1983 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - V, circa 1912-circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Victory Hall Association, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - W, circa 1912-circa 1952 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Williams, J. Scott, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Y, circa 1912-1986 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Z, circa 1912-circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Conferences, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 12-13)
  - Dinner for Ernest Peixotto, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Form Letters, 1940-1960 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Requests for Brochures, 1917-1921 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Requests for Protest, 1940-1941 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - List of Letters Received, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 18)
- Committee Files, 1909-1960s; Series 4; 0.3 Linear feet Box 5
  Committee files contain scattered correspondence, reports, lists, printed material, and memoranda documenting the work of standing and special committees.
  - Amend By-Laws and Constitution, 1921-1936 (Box 5, Folder 19-20)
  - Beautify New York City, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - Buildings and Sites, 1943 (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Coordination, 1938-1940 (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Current Work, 1917-1920 (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Dinners, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Education, 1917-1940 (Box 5, Folder 26-28)
  - Executive Committee, 1917-1921 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Fine Arts Federation, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Government and Art, 1940-1954 (Box 5, Folder 31-33)
  - Large Canvases, 1920-1921 (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Legislation, 1938-1939 (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
  - Medals and Awards, 1919-1921 (Box 5, Folder 37)
  - Membership, 1917-1941 (Box 5, Folder 38-39)
  - Mural Painting, 1909 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - Nominating Committee, 1917 (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - Professional Practice, 1917-1952 (Box 5, Folder 42-43)
  - Proposed Art Building, 1921 (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Publicity, 1921-1940 (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Washington Relations, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 46-48)
  - List of Standing Committees, 1919-1941 (Box 5, Folder 49)
- Exhibition and Competition Files, 1917-1998; Series 5; 2 Linear feet Boxes 5-7
  This series is arranged in chronological order according to the earliest document found for a project. Folders containing material relating to the Bicentennial competitions likely include documents relating to all three projects.
  The bulk of this series consists of material relating to the three NSMP projects celebrating the 1976 U.S. Bicentennial, including the "Freedom Murals", "The Caravan of Freedom", and "Momentous Events in American History". Files include correspondence, printed material, plans, itineraries, scattered financial documents, applications, and some photographs documenting planning, execution of work by members, fundraising, and publicity. Included is an audio cassette recording entitled "Momentous Events at Nabisco." A file for the Mural Night Forum includes a letter and typed remarks given by Elizabeth McCausland. There is a videocassette recording of a dedication of a mural by David Garrison in Fort Madison, Iowa.
  - Red Cross Canteen Project, 1917-1919 (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - George W. Breech Memorial Exhibition, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Portland, Oregon Exhibition, 1921-1925 (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Architectural League, 1921-1922 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Church Competition, 1937-1938 (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Bronx High School of Science, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Department Store Competition, 1939 (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Federal Art Project, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - Municipal Art Society Exhibition, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Mural Night Forum, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Public Works of Art Competition, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Selection of Fine Arts, Recommendations, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - Subway Murals, New York City, 1939-1940 (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - World's Fair Competition, 1939-1941 (Box 5, Folder 63-65)
  - Whitney Museum Exhibition, 1940-1941 (Box 5, Folder 66-67)
  - Whitney Museum Exhibition, 1940-1941 (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - Ernest Peixotto Memorial, 1942-1950 (Box 6, Folder 4-5)
  - Architectural League Exhibition, 1947 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Metropolitan Museum Exhibition, 1958 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - New York State Thruway Authority Competition, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bicentennial Competitions, 1973-1982 (Box 6, Folder 9-36)
  - Bicentennial Competitions, 1976-1998 (Box 7, Folder 1-17)
  - Bicentennial Competitions, Momentous Events at Nabisco, circa 1980; 1 Sound cassettes (Box 7, Folder 18)
  - 100th Anniversary Exhibition, 1995 (Box 7, Folder 19)
  - Dedication of Mural by David Garrison, Fort Madison, Iowa, 1997; 1 Videocassettes (VHS) (Box 7, Folder 20)
  - Mexico International Exhibition, 1997 (Box 7, Folder 21)
  - Art Students League Exhibition, 1998 (Box 7, Folder 22-23)
- Artist Files, 1915-1990s; Series 6; 1.3 Linear feet Boxes 7-8, 18
  Artist files may include resumes, correspondence, photographs of works of art. The bulk of the material dates from the 1960s to the 1990s. Earlier material consists of general artist biographies. Files are found for Robert P. Archer, Tom Capuccio, Peggy Delport, Dean Fausett, Michael Glickman, Robert J. Harding, Frank Mason, James Penny, and Elias River, among others.
  - General Artist Biographies, 1915-1944 (Box 7, Folder 24)
  - General Slide Lists, circa 1920 (Box 7, Folder 25)
  - A, 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 26)
  - B, 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 27-28)
  - C, 1960s-1990s (Box 7, Folder 29)
  - C, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - D, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - E, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - F, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - G, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - H, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - J, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - K, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - L, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - M, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 10-11)
  - N, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - O, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - P, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - R, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - S, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - T, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 17-18)
  - V, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - W, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 20-21)
  - Y, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Z, 1960s-1990s (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Oversized Photos of Works of Art, circa 1960-circa 1980 (Box 18, Folder 2)
- Financial and Legal Records, 1895-1996; Series 7; 1.5 Linear feet Boxes 8-10
  This series consists primarily of the treasurers' files containing correspondence regarding the payment of dues and financial reports. Other materials found here include ledgers and cash books, the majority of which are organized by member and note the payment date of dues received. Banking records consist of permission forms noting which officers are allowed access to the society's bank accounts. Legal records include a draft of an agreement and records relating to changing the name of the society in 1937.
  - Treasurer Files, 1895-1917 (Box 8, Folder 24-25)
  - Treasurer Files, 1917-1996 (Box 9, Folder 1-11)
  - Ledgers, Cash Books, 1895-1950s (Box 9, Folder 12-20)
  - Banking Material, Permissions, 1934-1952 (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - Tax Preparation and Exemption Records, 1944-1980 (Box 10, Folder 3-5)
  - Agreement, Draft, circa 1920 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Name Change Records, 1937 (Box 10, Folder 7)
  - Entrance Fee Receipts, 1940 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Receipts, Bills, and Invoices, 1938-1966 (Box 10, Folder 9-17)
- Printed Material, 1915-2000; Series 8; 0.9 Linear feet Boxes 10-11
  Exhibition catalogs and annoucements, informational brochures and pamphlets, newsletters, and a portfolio of members' works were published by National Society of Mural Painters. Clippings concern the society's members and its activities.
  - Admission Tickets and Printing Plate, 1923 (Box 10, Folder 18-19)
  - Clippings, 1934-1990 (Box 10, Folder 20-23)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, 1915-1998 (Box 10, Folder 24-27)
  - Informational Brochures and Pamphlets, 1915-2000 (Box 10, Folder 28-34)
  - Newsletters, 1936-2000 (Box 10, Folder 35-41)
  - Portfolio, 1950-1952 (Box 10, Folder 42)
  - Portfolio, 1950-1952 (Box 11, Folder 1-3)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1970 (Box 11, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook, 1923-1935; Series 9; 0.2 Linear feet Box 11
  One mixed media scrapbook contains correspondence, clippings, invitations, exhibition announcements, and some reproductions of works of art.
  - Scrapbook 1, 1923-1935 (Box 11, Folder 5)
- Photographic Material, circa 1900-1997; Series 10; 2.5 Linear feet Boxes 12-18
  Photographic materials consists of scattered photographs, transparencies, lantern slides, and photo collages of members, artwork, members with their artwork, meetings, exhibitions, and events. The photo collages typically include a photo of the artist and examples of their work. Also found are lantern slides, mostly of works of art, and of Francis D. Millett in his studio and with his murals and of J. Scott Williams with his art. A list of the lantern slides is found within the records, but it is unclear whether the list corresponds to all or some of the lantern slides.
  - Exhibitions and Events, 1970s-1997 (Box 12, Folder 1-8)
  - Meetings, 1990s (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - Works of Art, 1970s-1990s (Box 12, Folder 10-11)
  - Transparencies, circa 1960 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - List of Lantern Slides, circa 1935 (Box 12, Folder 13)
  - Lantern Slides, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 13, Folder 1-6)
  - Lantern Slides, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 14, Folder 1-6)
  - Lantern Slides, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 15, Folder 1-6)
  - Lantern Slides, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 16, Folder 1-6)
  - Lantern Slides, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 17, Folder 1-4)
  - Oversized Photo Collages, circa 1995 (Box 18, Folder 1)